When it comes to the Middle East issue for me...
中东问题对我来讲的话
Is something I've only discussed once.
是一个我只谈过一次的问题
An issue I've only discussed once.
只谈过一次的问题
In that ancient video
在那个远古的视频里
I once talked about a certain way of thinking back then
我就讲过一个当时的一个呃思维
which is not to offend small-minded people
就是不要得罪小人啊
how to put it
尤其是呃怎么说
a country like Israel, how should I say
以色列这样的国家还是一个比较怎么说呢
is very much like a small-minded person in life
非常就像生活当中的小人一样
if you offend them
你得罪他
troubles will pile up
麻烦会非常多
if you confront them directly
你跟他直接对抗
they won’t confront you head-on
他不会跟你直接对抗啊
That's the kind of situation.
就是这么一种状态
So, how should we approach this kind of international relationship?
所以到底应该怎样对待这样的这种国际关系呢
Back then, I said not to provoke them.
那时候我就说不要惹他们
If you do provoke them,
惹他们来讲的话
they will cause you trouble on significant issues.
他会在一些重大问题上给你找麻烦啊
First, let's build up some armor.
首先咱们先叠个甲
The Middle East issue is a very complex one.
中东问题是一个很复杂的一个问题
Um,
呃
Around the start of the first Middle East War It's been 77 years now. If everyone wants to delve into the Middle East issues, they are incredibly complex. Um, all these grudges and entanglements date back to before 77 years ago.
大概从这个第一次中东战争的开始 现在已经77年了啊 如果大家想深入的研究中东问题来讲话 它是非常复杂的 呃 所有的这些恩怨情仇要从77年之前开始啊
It's also closely related to the support from the UK and the US.
也跟这个英美的支持有很大的关系啊
Regardless,
无论怎么样
the series of actions taken by Israel against the people of Gaza,
在这个以色列对加沙人民所做的这一系列的事
such behavior, to put it bluntly,
这种行为来讲的话
This would be considered a war crime.
这就属于啊战争罪行
It falls under the category of genocide.
属于种族灭绝genocide啊
Regardless of the circumstances,
无论怎么样
This is simply unjustifiable.
这个东西是说不过去的啊
When we look at it,
这个东西来讲的话
It can actually backfire.
其实他是会反噬的
At present,
从现在来讲的话
Israeli citizens' international travel,
以色列民众在这个国际上的这个通行
And they find that many places are
然后又发现有很多地方的人
I find them extremely repulsive
是非常非常反感他们的
So, when it comes to this matter
所以这个东西来讲
You've made your own international space smaller.
就是自己把自己的这个国际空间给做小了
But how can we put it when talking about this issue
但是这件事情来讲的话怎么说呢
It's like the Munich massacre incident
就像慕尼黑惨案那件事情一样
regarding that Hamas raid on their Music event
对这种呃这个哈马斯突袭这个他们的音乐会
Right?
这件事是吧
Israel's response was extremely strong
以色列的反应是非常非常强烈的
but they feel why the international community doesn't support them Why does the international community show so much sympathy for these people? So, to explain, the international public opinion is overwhelmingly one-sided. Generally speaking,
但是他就会觉得为什么国际社会不支持我 为什么国际社会对这些人这么同情 所以来讲的话 国际社会的他这个舆论是一边倒的 基本上来讲的话
at the beginning, there were still some people who sympathized with Israel,
最开始还有一部分人同情以色列
but as time went on,
当然后来慢慢的
as the Gaza situation progressed,
随着这个加沙这个进程过来以后
now there’s actually a state where everyone is calling for action against them.
现在其实已经有一种人人喊打的一种状态了
So, everyone feels that their actions have been extremely excessive.
所以都觉得他做的十分过分啊
would all condemn it
都会去谴责
but today, from what perspective should we consider
但是我们今天从一种什么样的角度去考虑
this issue
这个问题呢
speaking of which
就是他啊
Israel
以色列
could still potentially be the dominant power in the Middle East
仍然可能会成为中东的一个第一大势力啊
based on the analysis of international trends
就是从这个国际形势的推演上来算的
the U.S. military has
今天美军那边起起
deployed a significant number of aerial refueling tankers
上了那个大量的空中加油机啊
Flying over from the other side of the Atlantic
从这个大西洋那个那边飞过去啊
it's likely they are supporting Israel
应该就是支持以色列的
because he now has control over the airspace above Tehran
因为他现在已经控制了德黑兰的这个上空的
securing air superiority
制空权了啊
which means
也就是说
if we look at this from an international political perspective
其实如果我们从这个国际政治的角度出发
without any emotional bias, in a cold and objective manner
不带任何感情色彩去冷酷的
coldly analyzing this situation
冷酷的分析这件事情
you'll find that the suffering of the people in Gaza is profound This thing validates a very long-standing rule the law of the jungle in this world it's survival of the fittest it's very harsh there isn't really any country with the power
你会发现其实加沙人民遭受的苦难 这个东西就是验证了一个非常通行已久的法则 就是动物园法则 在这个世界上来讲 弱肉强食啊 非常的惨 不会有真正有哪个国家有实力啊
or the capability to mediate the situation
或者有能力去调停这件事情
because there is no country around which
因为没有哪个国家在他周围来讲是啊
basically has no formidable rivals
基本上没有强敌的
People say that the State of Israel is so small
大家说以色列国那么小
why doesn't it have formidable enemies?
为什么他没有强敌呢
That's because you have to look at the major players in the Middle East
就是因为你要看中东的几个大玩家
like Saudi Arabia and Iran
沙特伊朗啊
and Egypt, not to mention Tunisia
埃及跟这个那个这个要上说突尼斯了
Turkey should be the strongest power
土耳其土耳其的力量应该是最强的
Turkey, a secular country
土耳其世俗的这个这个他也是一个世俗化国家
although it's somewhat returning to the old path of religious influence
虽然现在有点走入这个宗教化的老路
it remains a very powerful nation
但是呢它仍然是一个非常强大的国家
And the Ottoman Empire
而且奥斯曼土耳其帝国
once extended its reach to the west
曾经啊那边打到那个那个西边打到哪来的
all the way to the Danube River
打到那个多瑙河啊
and in the east, it controlled Palestine
东边这边整个控制这个巴勒斯坦加
and Egypt, which was quite formidable
这个埃及是非常厉害的
It could be said that compared to the Eastern Roman Empire of old,
可以说就是比当年的东罗马帝国来讲的话
though it controlled slightly less territory
可能就少控制一点地儿
but its control over the Middle East was very strong due to religious factors He belongs to the same religion However, in other areas If you've read the history of the Middle East wars
但是他对中东的控制是非常强的啊 因为他的宗教问题啊 他是同一个宗教 但是呢这个其他几个地方呢 如果你看过这个中东的这个这个战争史
You'll find this is the Middle East War for the nth time.
你会发现这个第几次中东战争
From the first to the fourth
从第一次到第四次啊
In terms of Egypt's military capability
埃及的军事能力来讲的话
It has generally been weaker
一直是比较弱的啊
There were times when it was strong
其实有强的时候
But when you consider these Arab countries together
但是就是这些阿拉伯国家加在一起
When we talk about Arab countries as a whole,
我们说阿拉伯国家加在一起来讲的话
due to the strategy we have adopted,
因为咱们采取的这个策略
our diplomatic approach has been to facilitate the reconciliation between Iran and Saudi Arabia.
外交策略呢是这个促进这个伊朗跟沙特和解
As a responsible major country,
咱们一个负责任的大国啊
in many issues,
咱们在很多问题上来讲的话
we have maintained a neutral stance.
就是都是采取中立的态度
However, regarding the excessive actions taken by Israel recently,
但是呢对于现在以色列做了很多过分的事儿
we have taken measures to stop them.
咱们是加以制止的
I have always believed that neutrality can be detrimental to oneself.
我一向认为中立是对自己不利啊
Such a choice is beneficial for world peace
对世界和平有利的这么一种选择
For instance, our neutrality in the Russia-Ukraine conflict
比如说咱们在俄乌冲突上的不站队的问题
Actually, taking sides
其实站队来讲的话
Can be advantageous for one's diplomatic gains
是对自己的外交的得意是有利的
Lian Yun once said
连云我说过
If you support the winning side The winning side will thank you If you support the losing side The losing side will also thank you Only you remain neutral The winning side feels you didn’t help them They will resent you for it The losing side thinks you didn’t sympathize with them
你支持胜利的一方 胜利的一方会感谢你 你支持失败的一方 失败一方也会感谢你 唯独就是你中立 胜利的一方觉得你没帮忙 他会那么怨恨你 失败的一方觉得你没有同情他
Not showing pity will also make them blame you
没有可怜他也会埋怨你
So, to maintain neutrality
所以做中立来讲
You must have sufficient strength and be powerful
是必须要有足够的实力和强大的
This ability to stay out of the conflict
这个置身事外的能力的
Especially when many countries are in conflict now
特别是现在会有很多国家啊进行冲突的时候
Let's all look at our expressions first
都先看咱们的脸色
It's kind of like the Minister of Civil Affairs in Japan.
就有点像日本的那个总务司令似的
As the top daimyo of the Warring States period
你作为一个战国第一大名啊
Many people will surely understand your thoughts and stance
很多人肯定会了解你的这个想法和立场
Whoever you support will win
因为你支持谁谁就会赢
When it comes to the issue of Israel
对于以色列这个问题的时候
We need to approach this with a calm mindset
大家要冷静的看待这个东西
That's right
是这样
Given his current position
因为他现在来讲的话
It can be said that there's no match for it in the Middle East.
可以说在中东完全没有对手呃
Saudi Arabia
沙特啊
and Iran
跟这个伊朗
and Turkey
跟这个这个土耳其
and Egypt are different
跟这个埃及不一样
because, to put it simply
因为来讲的话
there are only three types of regimes in the Middle East
中东只有三种政权
one is a theocratic regime
一个是政教合一的政权
like Iran, for example
像这个伊朗这样啊
If you've seen that film
你要是看过那个电影
I grew up in Iran
我在伊朗长大
you'd know how the people of Iran feel about their current leader, Khamenei and what they think of this government The domestic situation is also very complex, with various forces intertwined From the perspective of ordinary Iranians
你就会知道伊朗他民众 他对于他现在的这个哈梅内伊 这政府大概是什么样的感觉 他在国内也是各种各样的势力错综复杂啊 从这个伊朗普通民众的角度来讲啊
When I was in France
你像我在法国的时候
I met quite a few Iranian exiles
我就接触过不少的这个伊朗的流亡者啊
There are a great many people in the art industry.
从事艺术行业的非常非常多啊
They are incredibly talented.
非常有才华
And when you look at my time in Canada,
然后你要在看我在加拿大的时候
I was taking international relations classes.
那时候上国际关系课
At that time, the international relations class was taught by an elderly lady.
那个时候国际关系课是一个老太太
She was also a think tank member from Israel.
她也是以色列的一个智囊
Although she was Canadian,
他虽然是加拿大人
she was of Jewish descent.
但是她是犹太人啊
A think tank member from Israel.
以色列的智囊
Back then, we had classmates
那个时候就有我们那个同学啊
including Libyans
就有利比亚人
and Tunisians
还有突尼斯人
who pointed at this elderly lady and said
然后就指着这个老太太说
A woman
一个女人
how could a Jewish woman teach us?
怎么一个犹太女人怎么能给我们上课呢
and then they left the classroom
然后从教室就出去了
it was during the time of the conflict in Syria
那个时候正好是这个叙利亚的时候
the civil war
内战的时候啊
There are quite a few films by Mughal.
穆加哈电影比较多一点啊
So, this experience of studying abroad
所以其实这个在国外读书的这个经历
has given me a variety of
也给我了各种各样的
opportunities to interact with people from different backgrounds.
跟各种各样的人的接触的一个这个过程
For example, Iraqis,
比如说伊拉克人啊
Syrians,
比如说叙利亚人
and Libyans.
比如说利比亚人啊
Their thoughts and perspectives vary greatly. So you'll find that, when it comes to the Middle East, Let's include all these major countries. Like Saudi Arabia, Iran, and Egypt. Egypt was previously under military rule.
他们不同的这个人的思想是不一样的 所以你会发现其实在中东来讲的话啊 咱们把这些大国家都算上啊 这个沙特伊朗跟这个那个埃及 埃及他之前是军人政权啊
Speaking of Saudi Arabia,
呃以沙特呢来讲呢
We're talking about a federation of emirates.
咱们说咱们就是联合酋长制
It's a kind of
它是一种啊
How to put it,
怎么说呢
It can be described as a feudal monarchy.
可以说是一种封建王朝国家
For example, Jordan is similar.
比如说约旦也是啊
The UAE
阿联酋啊
UAE
UAE啊
These things are
这些东西都是
But there is no military power in the Middle East
但是就是在中东没有一个军事实力
A country with very strong industrial capabilities
工业能力非常强的一个国家
That can rival Israel
能够跟以色列抗衡啊
So speaking of it
所以来讲的话
You see, Saudi Arabia is far from it
你看沙特离他远啊
Israel’s Netanyahu
以色列那内塔尼塔尼亚胡啊
He sent a map
发过一张地图
basically showing what kind of territory a greater Israel might want in the future
就是说啊大的以色列将来是想要什么样领土
how extensive it would be
有多大
including parts of Saudi Arabia and Egypt
他把这个沙特跟那个埃及都算进去了
So, in terms of military strength and the level of infiltration
所以从这个军事力和这个被渗透程度来讲的话
these three countries are relatively weak
这三个国家来讲其实都是比较弱的
Turkey is the only one that’s stronger
唯独土耳其强一些
but Turkey has its own, how should I put it,
但是土耳其有自己的这个怎么说呢
its own interests
有自己的这个利益啊
It has its own interests with the Turks
有自己的犯这个突厥的这个利益啊
Arabs are Arabs
阿拉伯是阿拉伯人
Iranians are Iranians These are different, you see Persians are Persians However, Arab countries can't fully unite together it's impossible to unite because it's a matter of systems and local customs
伊朗人是伊朗人啊 这是不一样的哈 波斯人是波斯人 但是呢阿拉伯国家也没有办法 完完全全团结在一起啊 团结在一起也不可能 因为这是一个制度和这地方的习惯的问题啊
What kind of nation are you establishing?
你成立成立一个什么样的国家
Are you a federation or a vast empire?
你是一个联合的联邦还是一个大的帝国啊
How is it structured?
是怎么样
Who has such military power?
谁有这样的军事力
To be able to conquer each other?
能够互相吞并对方
To be honest, the reason the Middle East is the way it is today
其实来讲咱们说中东之所以到今天是这样
You'll find
你会发现
It's due to the division of spheres of influence by European powers back then.
其实是欧洲列强当年的势力范围的这种划分
For instance, take Egypt
比如你像埃及
There are also British and French influences
还有英法的势力
Lebanon has French influence
黎巴嫩有法国的势力
Saudi Arabia has British and American influence
沙特来讲有英美的势力
Speaking of Iran
伊朗来讲的话
it has various influences from different countries, including the Soviet Union
他又有各国的哈苏联的这种各样的势力
each controlling its own territory
他其实他来讲他是各控制一方
So, the Middle East has seen thousands of years of tribal conflicts
所以中东首先啊打了上千年很多部族冲突
ethnic conflicts
人种冲突
and religious conflicts that are hard to reconcile
宗教冲突啊是很难弥合的
It's really difficult to do that
是很难去那什么的
So, when we talk about it
所以来讲的话
In the future, if it happens
将来的有可能来讲的话
They could be picked off one by one by Israel
就会被以色列各个击破啊
This is a very likely scenario So you see, this time Israel has this issue When this crisis emerges They seek help from the five permanent members of the UN Security Council But notably, not from China Because China is a responsible major country
这个是非常有可能的一种情况 所以你看以色列这次他出现这种问题 出现这种危机的时候 他向联合国五常求助 但唯独没有中国 因为我们中国是一个负责任的大国啊
a prominent figure with a strong humanist ideology
是一个非常具有人道主义思想的大家
Look at what we're talking about today
你看今天我们就说呃
In many issues
很多问题上来讲的话
People tend to curse them
大家对他们都是各种诅咒啊啊啊
You finally got what you deserved
你终于挨打了
How are you doing
你怎么样
You must be feeling terrible and all
你很难受啊之类的
Now you finally understand the dire consequences of war
你现在终于知道这战争的恶果了
I think this is reflected in the sense of justice of our ordinary people.
我觉得这一点就体现在我们的这个老百姓来讲
They are very principled.
是非常有正义感的
They are willing to stand on the side of the underdog.
是愿意站在弱者一方
In the context of international politics,
这个东西在国际政治场合来讲
this is something that is hard to come by.
是非常来之不易的
It’s a remarkable act.
是非常了不起的一种行为
However, when it comes to diplomacy and politics,
但是作为外交跟这个政治上来考虑
especially from an intelligence perspective,
特别是从情报角度来讲考虑的话
often, one must be more cold-blooded in their speech.
很多的时候来讲话必须要冷血一些
We need to stay calm.
必须要冷静一些啊
As everyone knows,
大家也知道
the reason Israel was able to conduct
就是这次以色列之所以能对伊朗进行
such a successful targeted strike on Iran
这么成功的定点清除袭击呢
also related to Mossad's intelligence gathering capabilities
也跟这个摩萨德的这个情报掌握能力
its ability to recruit and infiltrate.
策反能力跟那个渗透能力有非常大的关系啊
Mossad is renowned for its strength and its reputation are closely tied to its early activities. I would say the most powerful intelligence organization in the world This intelligence organization should be Mossad.
说摩萨德之所以强大 之所以到那什么来讲话 他跟他这个早期的活动是有很大关系的啊 可以说我认为现在天下第一大的 这个情报组织呢应该是摩萨德
Secondly,
第二来讲的话
it should be Russia.
应该是这个俄罗斯啊
Thirdly, it’s the United Kingdom.
第三应该是英国
Fourth comes the CIA and the like.
第四才到CIA之类的啊
But many people say it’s just like that.
但是很多人说这个就是这样
You have no idea how powerful our country is.
你对祖国的强大一无所知
It’s like this.
这个东西是这样的
The motherland is this powerful.
祖国是这个强大的
It's not on the list, though.
不在排名之内啊
But you need to know about this Mossad
但是你要知道这个摩萨德
has an extremely strong capability.
他这个能力是非常强啊
Once you become an enemy of Mossad
一旦与摩萨德为敌
I mean, you can have a less friendly relationship with Israel,
我说可以与以色列啊关系不交好
But the relationship with Mossad must be maintained.
但是摩萨德的这个关系一定要保持一个呃
at the very least, keep in touch.
起码要保持接触
That's for sure.
这个是肯定的
Because his ability is exceptionally strong
因为他的这个能力十分的强
To go back to the earliest times
可以说从最早来讲
The Israelis I know
我认识的以色列人
You see
你看啊
Starting from 2001
从2001年开始
I've known Israeli students coming to China
我就认识以色列来华的大学生啊
These people, from a young age
这些人从小来讲
I feel they have a very calm and clear mind
我觉得他就有非常的冷静的那种啊这种头脑啊
So you never really know what their true intentions are So, a lot of times, you see, it's just like this. Back then, there was a director from MI6, right? Now, the director used to be a foreign teacher here. So, in many ways, the mutual exchange of personnel is quite common.
所以来讲你不知道他到底啊是来干什么的 所以很多时候你看就是这个 那会儿不是说m i six的一个局长吗 现在局长以前在咱们这边当外教了啊 所以很多来讲 这个互相之间互派这种状况很正常啊
Quite common.
很正常
When it comes to low-intensity intelligence gathering,
他进行一些低烈度的情报收集来讲的话
it's very normal.
是很正常
But you could tell back then that these people were involved.
但你那时候就看出来这些人来讲
He was closely associated with the early Chinese internet, particularly MSN.
他跟那个早期的中国网络特别MSN啊
There are elements that have seeped in.
还有一些东西它是有渗透
They have had an impact.
它是有影响的啊
We can't afford to be complacent.
不能掉以轻心
For many of these issues,
很多这种问题来讲
before they act out or commit significant events,
在他未发作或者他未做一些重大的事件之前呢
you don't have enough evidence to prove it,
你又没有足够的证据证
or sufficient grounds to arrest them.
足够的理由去逮捕他
That's how it is.
这个东西就是这样
So, to talk about it
所以来讲的话
In the long term
长期来讲的话
Mossad's infiltration into various countries around the world has been highly successful.
摩萨德对世界各国的渗透是非常成功的
Another point to consider
还有一点来讲
We need to understand that the Russians
咱们要知道就是俄罗斯人啊
When it comes to the British
英国人他们来讲
They are all Caucasians
他们都是白种人
It's relatively easier for Caucasians to infiltrate each other
白种人之间相互渗透也是比较容易的啊
For example, if you send a few people to the United States
真是你比如说你派几个人去美国了啊
Send a few people to Canada.
派几个人去加拿大了啊
Often blend into the crowd.
经常撒在人堆里
You can’t tell.
你是看不出来的
But it’s different in Asian countries.
但是亚洲国家都不一样
You’re Chinese.
你中国人
Japanese.
日本人
Korean.
韩国人
Go there and talk about it.
你去那儿来讲
You really stand out. Often times, if you're in an Arab country and suddenly see a Chinese person, or if you're in Russia and suddenly see a Chinese person, Or you suddenly see a Chinese person in America without exception, they stand out easily. In this regard,
你是很招眼 很多的时候来讲 你到阿拉伯国家突然看见一个中国人 或者你到俄罗斯突然看见一个中国人 或者你在美国突然看见一个中国人 无一例外就是他是很容易被发现的 就是这东西来讲的话
so when it comes to natural intelligence-gathering capabilities,
所以从天然的获情能力上来讲
We are comparing ourselves to Mossad, to Russia, and to the UK.
咱们比摩萨德比这个俄罗斯比英国啊
and we are also not as good as the United States.
要比美国要差一些啊
This is a disadvantage of human nature.
这是人种的一个劣势所在啊
Of course, it doesn't really matter.
当然来讲的话这个东西也无所谓
Because in many situations, we often maintain a neutral position.
因为咱们在一些时候很多身份的时候
Which can actually be more convenient.
是因为是保持中立的
This thing varies from person to person.
反而更方便啊
But regardless of that,
这个东西就是啊因人而异
From my perspective,
但是无论怎么说
From my perspective
就是从我的这个这个角度判断来讲的话
has industrial capabilities
有工业能力
if a country with some organizational capabilities is taken down
有一定组织能力的这国家打下去的话
it would have no rivals in the Middle East
其实他在中东就没有对手了
which is truly alarming
这一点就非常可怕了
if there are no rivals in the Middle East
如果在中东没有对手
and it is the only one with nuclear weapons
他又是一个唯一拥有核武器的
of course
当然来讲的话
Saudi Arabia has them too
沙特也有啊
speaking of this country
这个国家来讲的话
This is rather subtle.
这个就是比较微妙了
So our attitude going forward
所以咱们的态度就接下来
will determine the future of the Middle East.
决定了中东未来的命运
Actually, this is quite interesting.
其实这个就比较有意思
Speaking from a public perspective,
从民间来讲的话
people condemn the attacks on Gaza. This is correct. However, from a diplomatic standpoint, how close should we maintain our relationship with Israel? This is a rather delicate matter. If you maintain too much distance,
谴责他们这个去攻击加沙的群众 这个是对的 但是从这个啊从这个外交的角度来讲 跟以色列到底保持多远的距离啊 这个东西就比较微妙了 你保持太远的距离
it could turn into a bridgehead for other major powers to attack us.
他就会成为其他大国进攻咱们的一个桥头堡
or exclusively for our use,
或者说仅供咱们的
whether it’s economically,
不管是从这个经济上
politically,
政治上
militarily,
军事上
diplomatically speaking,
外交上来讲
especially in terms of intelligence.
特别是情报方面来讲啊
He would be a negative factor for us.
他就会作为咱们的一个怎么说不利因素存在
However, if you maintain a certain level of contact with him,
但是呢如果你跟他保持一定程度的接触的话
Actually, Jews are good at business.
其实犹太人是善于做生意的
For them,
他们来讲的话
Many times, for money, they don't have as many principles.
其实很多的时候为了金钱没有那么多的原则啊
So in many cases,
所以很多的时候来讲
If you are in the current international situation,
如果你在现在这种国际上
When the criticism against him is quite intense,
对他声讨比较厉害的时候啊
Or when his people are suffering more
或者说现在他民众比较遭致
And he is currently facing an existential crisis militarily.
还有他在军事上现在处于一个存亡危机的时候
If there is a certain level of continued contact and engagement with him,
如果对他有一定一定程度上的保持联系接触啊
or expressing concern about his survival status,
或者来讲对其生存地位表示担忧
or something along those lines, having such an attitude, it's like the unpopular student in your class, who is very capable, comes from a wealthy family, and doesn't get along well with classmates.
或者怎么样的话 有一种这样的态度来讲的话 就像你们班一个不招人待见的同学啊 他很有实力 家里很有钱啊 然后他跟同学关系都不好
When he was being criticized by the whole class,
当他被全班同学骂的时候呢
as someone who aspires to be the class president,
你作为一个啊将来要竞选班长的人
you need to consider how to play this card,
你就要考虑到这张牌该怎么打啊
try to use this moment to your advantage,
尽量把它能通过这个时候来讲买入啊
bringing him into your fold is actually the simplest solution,
收之麾下其实是最简单的
considering his reputation on the international stage,
因为他在这时候在国际上的风评
along with his military strategy,
跟他他在军事上的这个策略
and his overall approach to geopolitics,
跟他在整个这个地缘政治上的这个
in the context of the ongoing crisis.
储存的危机来讲
You could say it was the lowest point.
可以说是最低点
Once he won, though,
一旦到他赢了啊
he successfully defeated Iran completely.
把伊朗完全成功干掉了啊
After suppressing Saudi Arabia and Egypt,
在压制了沙特跟那个埃及
After completing the operations in the Gaza Strip and Jordan
在完成了对加沙地带和约旦
as well as the West Bank and other regions,
河西岸等各地的统合
considering his own position,
而且他本身来讲的话
Lebanon,
黎巴嫩
Syria
叙利亚
Countries like Jordan can't really pose a threat to him.
约旦这些国家都威胁不了他
After all, Jordan wouldn't be hostile towards him.
约旦首先就不会跟他敌对对吧
And Egypt wouldn't be hostile either.
也其实埃及也不会跟他敌对啊
You should know that Egypt is heavily influenced by Israel. I believe Saudi Arabia is also significantly influenced. Otherwise, he wouldn't place Egypt and Saudi Arabia together on the map. When it comes to Syria, there's virtually no control,
你要知道埃及被以色列渗透的是很厉害的 沙特我相信也是非常的厉害 否则他不会在版图上把埃及跟沙特放在一起啊 呃叙利亚来讲的话 完全没有什么控制啊
no capability to strike him.
打击他的能力
So, in a situation where he has naval and air superiority,
所以完全就是他在这个海空军占优的情况下呢
What exactly does that mean?
是完完全全是什么
His only distinctive feature is,
他唯一的特点就是他这个啊
Why does he want to gather all the Israelis back?
为什么他要招取全球的以色列人回去呢
When it comes to ground warfare,
他要唯一就是地面战争来讲
He might not have such a large pool of troops,
他可能没有那么大的兵源啊
Unable to control such a vast occupied territory,
没有办法控制那么大的占领地
So if he really wants to build up his forces,
所以他如果真正想暴兵啊
To control a large swath of territory in the Middle East.
想控制中东一大片领土的话
He still faces significant obstacles
还是他要面临很大的障碍
So at this point
所以在这个时候来讲的话
Everyone needs to see that the Middle East situation remains unchanged
大家要看到中东局势不变化
That's most beneficial for us
对咱们是最有利的啊
If the Middle East situation changes rapidly
所以来讲的话中东局势如果迅速变化
If it turns in his favor
如果变得对他有利来讲的话
Why would he do this
他为什么要这么干
Because the United States' influence is also declining
因为美国现在的影响力也日渐衰弱
He will certainly take advantage of the weakened influence in the American market.
他一定会趁在美国市场的衰弱的影响力
Before the military influence completely waned
军事影响完完全全衰弱之前
not many people took it seriously, did they?
没有大家在当他回事吧
Because he has a military alliance treaty with the United States This treaty is different from the ones with Japan and South Korea As Japan and South Korea have U.S. troops stationed there Israel, on the other hand, is in a military alliance So, under this military alliance
因为他跟美国是有军事同盟的条约的啊 他跟那个日本韩国那种条约还不一样 因为日本韩国是驻军啊 这个以色列是就军事同盟这个关系 所以军事同盟
the U.S. has to provide refueling aircraft
所以他就要向他提供加油机啊
and bombers, among other things
提供轰炸机之类的
Everyone knows that the First Middle East War was fought like this.
大家知道第一次中东战争就是这么打下来的
It was tacitly approved by the United States.
是美国默许的
So, in a sense, it's a little bully that the U.S. has propped up in the Middle East.
所以他来讲就是在中东的扶植的一个小霸王
Without Israel,
没有以色列
there would be other U.S. client states.
也会有美国的其他仆从国啊
This is a very normal thing.
这是很正常的事情
It's just that this is a very useful tool.
只不过这是一个很好利用的一个东西
But a country's population growth,
但是一个国家从他人口发展
its military manpower,
从他兵源啊
Given his control capabilities
从他这个控制能力来讲
he wouldn't have grown so rapidly
他不会迅速发展那么大
But in the state of affairs over the next few decades
但是在未来几十年的这个状态
if we continue to be in an adversarial relationship with him
如果咱们一直跟他是敌对状态
from the government to the public, being in an adversarial state
就是从官方到民间都是敌对的状态来讲的话
it would be detrimental to us
对咱们来讲不利
but if we maintain a moderate level of engagement
但是如果咱们保持一个适当的接触的话
in many cases
其实很多情况下啊
we can obtain intelligence through the Israeli network about the British
就是通过以色列人拿的情报网去知道英国人啊
What about the Russians?
俄罗斯人啊
What are the Americans up to?
美国人在干什么来讲
Actually, this is quite convenient.
其实这是非常方便的啊
If there is some communication,
如果有一定交流的话
Because throughout history, There have been various examples. When we engage with the two major powers, the US and the USSR, In this balance of power game, You'll find that some crucial intelligence matters a lot. These can be obtained through them.
因为这个东西在这个历史上 是有各种各样例子的 我们在跟美苏两大国进行这个 这个平衡博弈的时候 你会发现如果啊这些东西有些重要情报来讲 是可以通过他们来获得的
So, in the realm of international politics,
所以在国际政治上来讲的话
If it’s not something that directly impacts our interests,
如果不是直接影响咱们利益的事情呢
A lot of things can be negotiated and traded.
完全很多东西都是可以做交易
Some say that conscience shouldn’t be traded,
然有人说跟良心不能做交易
But in the context of international politics,
但是在国际政治场合上来讲
Often times,
很多的时候来讲
It has nothing to do with conscience,
跟良心没有关系
It’s all about power.
跟实力有关系啊
No one really has the capability to deploy ground forces into Gaza.
不会有人真正有能力投放地面部队到加沙去
So the Gaza issue seems to be in a deadlock.
所以加沙的问题无解啊
All we can do is sympathize.
大家只能同情
Or, at best, accept their refugees.
大家只能或者说接受他的难民
Of course, we all know what accepting Palestinian refugees entails.
当然接受巴勒斯坦难民是什么样的结果
Everyone is aware of that.
大家也知道啊
Many historical events
历史上很多事情
can be researched online to understand what has transpired.
咱们可以去百度一下到底发生了些什么
Why Arab countries are sometimes reluctant to accept them
阿拉伯国家为什么有时候不愿意接受
The situation of Palestinian refugees is also intertwined.
巴勒斯坦难民也是有关系的
So, in many cases,
所以很多的时候来讲的话
the Middle East issue is very complex.
就是中东的问题非常复杂
There are sectarian conflicts,
又有教派矛盾
ethnic conflicts,
又有民族矛盾
state conflicts,
又有国家矛盾
and tribal disputes.
又有部落矛盾啊
It's a powder keg.
所以是一个火药桶
But if you don't get involved,
但是如果你不去介入
don't observe,
不去观察
in many cases, it doesn't reflect the responsibility of a modern major power. So, no matter what, in terms of diplomacy, I think we should be in line with the country's stance. We are just ordinary people, right? We don't have much influence on foreign policy decisions,
很多的时候来讲的话 也不是一个现代负责任大国的这种感觉 所以来讲的话 无论怎么样 在外交上来讲的话 我觉得啊首先我们与国家高度一致 我们就是老百姓 对不对 我们也不会说对这个外交决策
military decisions,
军事决策
or various intelligence decisions.
各种各样的情报上的决策有什么影响力
But no matter what,
但是无论怎么样
from a civilian perspective,
而且从一个民间的角度来讲
I think maintaining contact is important,
我觉得保持一个接触
keeping a certain level of foundation,
保持一个一定程度上的基础啊
not being completely adversarial.
不要完完全全敌对
This is a very, very delicate approach,
这是一个非常啊非常精妙的一种啊
how to put it,
这种怎么说呢
a brilliant move.
星耀的一种操作
If you completely cut ties,
如果你完完全全那什么来讲
they might fully align with the West,
切断了以后
which would certainly become a major threat to us.
完全他倒向西方
So that's how it is.
一定会成为咱们的一个心腹大患
If you put it in English, it's like,
所以这个东西就是这样
‘keep your friends close, but keep your enemies closer.’
如果你用用用用英文的一句话来说
You need to maintain a closer relationship with your enemies,
keep your friends close啊
especially potential enemies.
keep your enemies Closer啊
But Israel also understands this,
就是你要把敌人跟你的这个关系
we have significant interests in the Middle East,
特别是潜在的敌人关系更大
especially in energy supply from Iran and Saudi Arabia,
但是以色列其实也是明白的呃
which is crucial for us.
咱们在中东有很强大的利益啊
Iran, Saudi Arabia, and Russia are the main options,
特别是伊朗跟沙特的这个能源供应
and our international relations with Russia are particularly delicate.
对咱们来讲是至关重要的啊
So it can't be described in simple terms. In international politics, there's not much talk of emotion, it's more about the exchange of interests. So if you're interested in international relations in the future,
伊朗沙特俄罗斯其实就这三个选择 咱们跟俄罗斯之间的国际关系呢 更是非常之微妙啊 所以不能用简单的语言去形容 国际政治上来讲的话
I hope you can spare some time,
没有讲那么多感情
and consider pursuing a master's degree in this field,
更多是一种利益上的交换
to contribute to the prosperity and strength of our country in this area.
所以如果你将来对国际关系这个东西呢
And to be honest,
感兴趣呢
many things in international politics require a very cold and harsh perspective,
希望大家呢有空呢
because the world operates on the laws of the jungle.
将来呢往这个方向研究考这方面研究生啊